A Finding Aid to the James Brooks and Charlotte Park Papers, 1909-2010, bulk 1930-2010, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
James Brooks and Charlotte Park papers
1909-2010
bulk 1930-2010
Archives of American Art
Brooks, James, 1906-1992
AAA.broojame
Archival Resource Key
20.1 Linear feet
The papers of Abstract Expressionist painters James Brooks and Charlotte Park measure 18.7 linear feet and are dated 1909-2010, bulk 1930-2010. Correspondence, subject files, personal business records, printed material, and a sound recording document his painting career, interests, professional and personal activities. Also found are biographical materials, interviews, writings, and art work. The collection also includes papers of his wife, Abstract Expressionist painter Charlotte Park, regarding her painting career, personal life, activities as executor of James Brooks' estate, and some material concerning the James Brooks and Charlotte Park Brooks Foundation. There is a 1.4 linear foot addition to this collection donated in 2017 that includes 58 "week-at-a-glance" appointment books, three journals and one address/ telephone book of Charlotte Park; a hand written chronology with significant dates and notes; postcards and exhibition announcements sent to Charlotte and James; doodles; and a sketch, possibly by Don Kingman.
Biographical / Historical
James Brooks (1906-1992) and Charlotte Park (1919-2010) were Abstract Expressionist painters in East Hampton, N.Y. A native of St. Louis, Missouri, Brooks spent his childhood in Colorado, Oklahoma, Illinois, and Texas. He begn drawing as a young boy, finding inspiration in magazine illustrations and comic strips. Before moving to New York City in 1926, he studied at Southern Methodist University (1923-1924) and at the Dallas Art Institute.
In New York, Brooks studied illustration at the Grand Central Art School. After exposure to museums led him to differentiate between illustration and fine art, Brooks enrolled at Art Students League. During this period he supported himself by doing lettering for magazine advertisements. From 1936-1942 he participated in the WPA Federal Art Project, executing murals at Woodside Library, Queens, New York (destroyed); the Post Office, Little Falls, New Jersey; and his famous Flight at LaGuardia Airport's Marine Air Terminal (painted over in the 1950s and restored in 1980).
During World War II Brooks served in the United States Army as an art correspondent in Cairo. When at the Office of Special Services, Washington, DC, he met Charlotte Park who worked there as a graphic artist and later became his wife. The couple moved to New York City in 1945 and married in 1947. Brooks resumed friendships with artists he knew from the WPA including Philip Guston, Bradley Walker Tomlin, and Jackson Pollock. Brooks and Park were especially close with Pollock and Lee Krasner; after they moved to Long Island, Brooks and Park, soon followed, first to Montauk and later to the Springs, East Hampton, New York.
By the late 1940s, Brooks had turned away from figural painting in the social realist style and moved toward abstraction. In the early 1950s, he was experimenting with enamel, gouache, and diluted oil paints, staining various grounds in ways that produced interesting shapes, adding spontaneous splashes of color over which he painted more deliberately. In the 1960s he switched to acrylics, leading to wider use of color and broader strokes.
Peridot Gallery presented Brooks' first solo exhibition in 1949. He helped organize and participated in the famous Ninth Street Show of 1951, earning critical acclaim. This assured him a place in two of the Museum of Modern Art's most important exhibitions of the period, Twelve Americans (1956) and New American Painting (1958). He showed at the Stable Gallery, Kootz Gallery, Martha Jackson Gallery and others. During his lifetime Brooks enjoyed five traveling retrospective exhibitions.
Prizes and awards included Carnegie Institute's Pittsburgh International Exhibition 5th prize for painting (1952), The Art Institue of Chicago's 62nd American Exhibition Logan Medal and Prize for Painting (1957) and 64th American Exhibition Harris Prize (1961), The National Arts Club Medal (1985), and a citation of appreciation for Flight from The North Beach Club Marine Air Terminal, LaGuardia Airport (1986).
Brooks taught for nearly three decades: drawing at Columbia University (1947-1948) and lettering at Pratt Institute (1948-1955); was a visiting critic, Yale University (1955-1960), University of Pennsylvania (1971-1972), and Cooper Union (1975); and served on the Queens College faculty (1966-1969). In addition, he was an artist-in-residence at The American Academy in Rome (1963), the recipient of a Guggenheim Fellowship (1969), and a National Endowment for the Humanities Grant (1973).
Brooks developed Alzheimer's disease around 1985 and died in East Hampton, New York in 1992.
Charlotte Park graduated from the Yale School of Fine Art (1939) and during World War II, when working in Washington, D.C., she met James Brooks. They moved to New York City in 1945, where she studied with Australian artist Wallace Harrison. Park taught children's art classes at several private schools in the early 1950s and at the Museum of Modern Art, 1955-1967.
Park's approach to Abstract Expressionism featured curved or linear shapes with vibrant colors and dynamic brushstrokes. Tanager Gallery presented her first solo show in 1957 and her work was included in numerous group exhibitions from the 1950s through 2000s, mainly in New York City and Long Island. After Park's second solo exhibition, held in 1973 at Elaine Benson Gallery, Bridgehampton, New York, interest in her work revived; other one-person shows followed at Guild Hall (1979), Ingber Gallery (1980), and paired with James Brooks at Louise Himelfarb Gallery. The National Institute of Arts and Letters honored Park with its Art Award in 1974. Her work is in the permanent collections of the Parrish Art Museum, Guild Hall Museum, Telfair Museum of Art, and in many private collections.
Charlotte Park died in 2010.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Abstract Expressionist painters James Brooks and Charlotte Park measure 18.7 linear feet and are dated 1909-2010, bulk 1930-2010. Correspondence, subject files, personal business records, printed material, and a sound recording document his painting career, interests, professional and personal activities. Also found are biographical materials, interviews, writings, and art work. The collection also includes papers of his wife, Abstract Expressionist painter Charlotte Park, regarding her painting career, personal life, activities as executor of James Brooks' estate, and some material concerning the James Brooks and Charlotte Park Brooks Foundation. There is a 1.4 linear foot addition to this collection donated in 2017 that includes 58 "week-at-a-glance" appointment books, three journals and one address/ telephone book of Charlotte Park; a hand written chronology with significant dates and notes; postcards and exhibition announcements sent to Charlotte and James; doodles; and a sketch, possibly by Don Kingman.
Biographical materials include biographical notes and documents such as copies of birth and death certificates, curricula vitae, family history. Educational records are from Southern Methodist University and documentation of flight training courses at New York University. Brooks' military service in World War II is well documented by United States Army records with related correspondence. Also found is extensive documentation of his death and funeral.
Professional and personal correspondence is addressed to Brooks, the couple, and to Charlotte Park during the later years of Brooks' life when she managed his affairs. A significant amount of correspondence is categorized as art, autograph requests, personal, and teaching; also include is general correspondence that overlaps all categories. Art correspondence with museums, galleries, collectors, artists, and friends concerns exhibitions, Brooks' work, and invitations to exhibit, speak, or serve as a juror. Of note is the correspondence with Samuel M. Kootz Gallery. The personal correspondence is mainly social, and teaching correspondence consists largely of requests that he teach in summer programs, serve as a visiting artist/critic.
Six interviews with James Brooks are in the form of published and unpublished transcripts; a seventh is a sound recording with no known transcript. Charlotte Park participates in one interview.
Writings by Brooks are statements about his work and a tribute to Ilya Bolotowsky. Among the writings by others about Brooks are a catalog essay, academic papers, and lecture; also found are a few short pieces on miscellaneous topics. Three diaries include brief entries regarding his work, exhibitions, and activities.
Subject files maintained by Brooks concerning organizations, exhibitions, mural projects, a commission and teaching document his professional activities, relationships and interests. Personal business records concern appraisals, conservation, gifts, insurance, loans, sales, shipping, and storage of artwork. Gallery records include agreements, consignments, lists, and receipts. Also, there are accounts for lettering work and personal income tax returns.
Printed material is mostly exhibition announcements, invitations, catalogs, and checklists, as well as articles and reviews. The majority are about/mention Brooks or include reproductions of his work; some concern artist friends, former students, and others.
Artwork by Brooks consists of pencil and ink drawings, two sketchbooks, and "telephone doodles." Other artists include Adolph Gottlieb (ink drawing of sculpture), Philip Guston (three pencil drawings of Brooks), and William King (two silhouettes of Brooks).
Photographic materials (photographs, digital prints, negatives, slides, and color transparencies) provide extensive documentation of Brooks' artwork and, to a lesser extent, exhibitions.There are pictures of Brooks as a very young boy, though the most views of him date from the 1930s through 1980s, and with friends. Places include Brooks' homes and studios in Montauk, New York and the Springs, East Hampton, New York; travel to Maine, Oregon and California. Views of the Middle East from World War II show Brooks with colleagues, local people engaged in daily activities, and scenery. Also of note are a copy print of "The Irascibles" by Nina Leen, and attendees at the dedication of Flight dining in view of Brook's LaGuardia Ariport mural.
Charlotte Park papers document the professional career and personal life of the Abstract Expressionist painter, art teacher, and wife of James Brooks through correspondence, personal business records, exhibition records, printed material, and photographs. In addition, this series documents artwork in the estate of James Brooks and posthumous exhibitions. Twelve years younger than her husband, Park began handling business matters for him as he aged and developed Alzheimer's disease. She also served as his executor. In the 1990s, a curator assumed management of the artwork and loans for exhibitions. After the James Brooks and Charlotte Park Brooks Foundation was established in 2000, its director handled most business activities. Some copies of Foundation minutes and correspondence are found among Park's papers.
Separated Materials
Correspondence, interview transcripts, photographs, and printed material were loaned by James Brooks for microfilming in 1969 (reel N69-132). With the exception of an address book, a scrapbook, and a few photographs, Brooks donated almost all of the loan in 1979.
Related Materials
Also among the Archives of American Art's holdings are letters from James Brooks and Sean Scully, 1980-1989 addressed to Theodora ["Teddy"] S. Greenbaum, and an oral history interview with James Brooks conducted by Dorothy Seckler, 1965 June 10 and June 12.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was donated in 2013 by the James Brooks and Charlotte Brooks Foundation and an additional 1.4 linear feet donated 2017 by the Foundation. In 1979 James Brooks donated most of the material lent for microfilming in 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 11 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1924-1995 (Box 1, OV 19; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1928-1995 (Boxes 1-3; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, 1965-1990 (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1952-1999 (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Diaries, 1975-1984 (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 6: Subject Files, 1926-2001 (Boxes 3-5, OV 20; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 7: Personal Business Records, 1932-1992 (Boxes 5-6; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1928-1992 (Boxes 6-11, OV 21-OV 22; 4.8 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1930s-1992 (Box 11; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 10: Photographic Materials, 1909-2000s (Boxes 11-15; 4.1 linear feet)
Series 11: Charlotte Park papers, 1930s-2010 (Boxes 15-18, OV 23; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 12: Unprocessed Additition, circa 1930-2010 (Boxes 25-26; 1.4 linear feet)
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels N69-132 and 292-293 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Interviews; Drawings; Photographs; Diaries; World War, 1939-1945; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Abstract expressionism; New York University -- Students; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1907-1981; Southern Methodist University -- Students; United States. Army; Kootz Gallery (N.Y.); Park, Charlotte; King, William, 1925-2015; Guston, Philip, 1913-1980
- Biographical Materials, 1924-1995; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1, OV 19
  Scope and Contents
  Among the awards and certificates are: Carnegie Institute's Pittsburgh International Exhibition 5th Prize (1952); The Art Institute of Chicago 62nd American Exhibition Logan Medal and Prize for Painting (1957) and 64th American Exhibition Harris Prize (1961); and a citation of appreciation for Flight presented by The North Beach Club, Marine Air Terminal, LaGuardia Airport (1986). Biographical documents include powers of attorney, birth and death certificates, and a letter about his 1942 divorce from Mary MacDonald. World War II military records and related correspondence provide detailed information about his service in the Middle East. Condolence letters are included among the records concerning his funeral.
  - Address Books, undated; 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1952-1986; Archival Resource Key; Oversized materials housed in OV 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliographies, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Documents, 1942-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1960s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Calendar, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Curricula Vitae, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Educational Records, Southern Methodist University, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Educational Records, New York University, Flight Training, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Family History, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Funeral and Related Records, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Condolence Letters, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Expenses, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Grave Markers, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Graveside Service, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Memorial Tributes, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Obituaries, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Will, Probate, Letters of Testamentary, etc., 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Membership Certificates, 1972; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Military Records and related Correspondence, 1941-1946; 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Souvenirs, U.S. Army in Egypt, 1942-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oversized Certificate from Box 1, Folder 2, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 19)
- Correspondence, 1928-1990s; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Correspondence, both personal and professional in nature, is addressed to Brooks and to the couple. There is overlap between general correspondence and other categories. Art correspondence covers exhibitions, loans, commissions, projects; arrangements with museums and galleries; sales and consignments; as well as letters from friends and admirers of his work. Most personal correspondence from friends and colleagues is of a social nature. Teaching correspondence requests that Brooks consider opportunities to teach in various summer programs, participate in studio tours for students, or serve as a visiting artist/critic; also included are a few course rosters.
  Arrangement
  Correspondence – general and each of the categories designated by Brooks (art, autograph requests, personal, and teaching) – is arranged by year. Additional correspondence is scattered throughout the papers.
  - General, circa 1928-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-33)
  - General, 1964-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Art, circa 1960-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-24)
  - Art, Samuel M. Kootz Gallery Inc., 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Autograph Requests, circa 1970s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Personal, circa 1940-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Teaching, 1968-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Interviews, 1965-1990; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3
  This series consists of published and unpublished transcripts and a sound recording of interviews with Brooks conducted for a variety of purposes. Charlotte Park participates in the 1965 Vallière interview. Also found are a list of interviews and correspondence with some of the interviewers.
  Interviews are arranged chronologically.
  - James Brooks interviewed by Gladys Kashdin, 1965 March 8 (transcript), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - James Brooks interviewed by Dorothy Seckler, 1965 June 10 and June 12 (transcript), 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - James Brooks interviewed by James T. Vallière, 1965 November 9 (transcript), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - James Brooks interviewed by Karl Fortess, 1970 February (transcript), circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - James Brooks interviewed by April Kingsley (transcript), 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - James Brooks interviewed by Louise Svendsen, 1975; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - James Brooks interviewed by Ann Gibson (transcript), circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - List of James Brooks Interviews conducted 1952-late 1980s, circa 1975-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Interviewers, 1972-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Writings, 1952-1999; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3
  Among Brooks' writings are a working list for an unidentified 1962 exhibition, statements, and a tribute to Ilya Bolotowsky. Writings about Brooks include catalog essays by Stanley Kunitz for Berry Hill and by Carter Ratcliff for Gruenebaum Gallery, a paper by Donald Judd written while studying art history with Meyer Schapiro at Columbia University, and two articles about the restoration of the LaGuardia Airport mural, Flight. Also found is the text of a lecture by Helen Weinberg, "The Iconology of Self in James Brooks Paintings," delivered at the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center.
  - By Brooks, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Lists, circa 1962-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Pieces (written/published circa 1921-1976), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Statements and Quotations, 1950s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Tribute to Ilya Bolotowsky, circa 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - By Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - About Brooks – Catalog Essays and Academic Papers, undated; 1963-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - About Brooks – Lecture by Helen Weinberg at Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Topics, 1952-circa 1984, 1954-circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Quotes, undated, 1963-1980s, circa 1963-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Diaries, 1975-1984; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3
  Although titled quite differently, each of the three volumes consists of brief entries (often daily, sometimes sporadic) that record transactions, requests, ideas and decisions about his work, exhibitions, other business matters, and activities. Volume 2 includes very few entries.
  - Volume 1: "Log", 1975 February-1979 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Volume 2: "Lists of Letters Written and Dated", 1982 February-April; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Volume 3: "Notes and Diary", 1982 September-1984 February; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Subject Files, 1926-2001; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 2 Linear feet Boxes 3-5, OV 20
  Subject files may include a wide variety of materials - correspondence, printed material, photographs, and notes - in varying combinations. Those maintained by Brooks concerning organizations, exhibitions, projects, teaching, and a trip to Europe document his activities, professional interests, and relationships.
  Subject files are alphabetized by title. Additional files concerning Brooks exhibitions held after his death are found in the Charlotte Park papers (Series 11).
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1968-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29-32)
  - Artists Equity Association, Incorporated, 1975-1984; 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Century Association, 1968-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Corporate Art Group, 1981; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ediciones Poligrafia/SA, 1973-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Amarillo Art Center, Eight Modern Masters (1985 April 20-?), 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Benton Gallery, Contemporary Editions: Prints/Sculpture (1987 August 15-September 3), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Berry-Hill, James Brooks: The 1950s (1989 October 18-November 11), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Century Association (1988 January 5-?), 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)